A Guide to the Papers of Orland E. White, 1902-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Orland E. White 1902-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12767-a
This collection consists of 4000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.)
Acquisition Information
These papers were originally deposited by Mr. O. E. White in the Manuscripts Department of the University of Virginia Library. The several dates of deposit, as well as the Manuscripts Accession Number assigned to each, are as follows:
July 5, 1948 2978
June 8, 1950 2978-c
June 21, 1950 2927-d
July 5, 1955 2978-e
Feb. 16, 1968 2978- f.
Mr. White's daughters, Mrs. Winchester and Mrs. James Quarles, donated the papers to the University of Virginia in January and July of 1982.
Biographical/Historical Information
White, Orland Emile, biologist; b. Sibley, Ia. B. S., S. D. State College, 1909, M.S., 1911; M.S., Harvard, 1912; Sc.D., Bussey Instin. of Harvard, 1913: m. Loto Rollinstall Underwood, July, 1913; children - Margaret Underwood (Mrs. Dean Winchester), Prudence Wayne (Mrs. James Quarles). Nurseryman, Yankton, S.D., 1904; research asst., S.D. State College and experiment station, 1909-1910, instr. in botany, 1910-11; lab. teaching asst. in botany, Radcliffe Coll., 1912, in genetics, 1913; asst. curator plant breeding Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1913-1915, curator, 1916-1924, curator plant breeding and economic plants, 1914-1927; collaborator U.S. Dept. of Agr., 1915-18, 1919-1923, specialist, 1918-1919; botanist Mulford Exploration of Amazon Basin Expedition, 1921-1922; prof. agrl. biology and dir. Blandy Experimental Farm, U. of Va., since 1927; research scholar, U.S. Ednl. Found. In Burma and vis. prof., Univ. Coll., Mandalay and U. of Rangoon, 1950-1951, Fellow A.A.A.S.; mem. Nat. Research Council com. on fellowships in biology and agr., 1943-1945, chmn. panel on botany, growth com., med. div., 1945-1946; mem. Botanical Soc. of Am. (editorial bd., 1920-1921, council mem. genetics sectn., 1928, chmn, southeastern sect., 1943-1945), Am. Naturalist, Am. Genetics Assn., Genetics Soc. of Am., Tenn. Acad. Science, Washington Acad. Science, Va. Acad. Science (chmn. biol. sect., 1931), Rock Garden Soc. of Am. (chmn South Atlantic region, 1936-1938, 1941-43), John Burroughs Memorial Assn. (2d vice president, 1925-28, mem. bd. dirs. since 1928), Sigma XI. Clubs: Genetics (pres. 1944-1946), Harvard (Washington); Explorer's. Author numerous articles on plant genetics and cytology, origin of cultivated plants, cytogenetics of pisum, biology of fasciation, temperature tolerance in relation to mutation and geog. distribution. Mem. ed. bd. Am. Jour. of Botany, 1920-1921; editor genetics sect. of round table conf. on agr. and population increase, Inst. of Politics, Williamstown, Mass., 1925; rep. Brooklyn Botanic Garden on Inst. for Research in Tropical Am., 1923-27. (from Who's Who in America)
Scope and Content Information
The Orland E. White papers consist of ca. 4000 items (ca. 6 linear feet), 1902-1955, concerning all aspects of White's life as a professor, researcher, scientist, explorer, and husband. The collection includes correspondence, articles, reviews, research notes, a typescript and illustrations for Economic Plants, his journal of the Mulford Biological Exploration of the Amazon Basin, and student applications for Blandy Experimental Farm. Most of the material dates from White's years as Curator of the Brooklyn Botanic Garden (1916-1927) and as director of the Blandy Experimental Farm (1927-1955), although a number of items date from White's college years at South Dakota State College (ca. 1905-1909) and the Bussey Institution of Harvard University (1909-1913). Included in the correspondence are letters to and from the eminent naturalist John Burroughs.
Correspondents include Clara Barrus, Albert Francis Blakeslee, Charles Thomas Brues, Charles Stuart Gager, Lincoln Constance, Raymond Adams Butcher, Edward Murray East, Walter Samuel Flory, Montague Free, Lulu Odell Gaiser, Roman Kenk, Hui-Lin Li, Paul Christoph Mangelsdorf, Samuel Lewis Meyer, Bruce Dodson Reynolds, Harold Archie Senn, Hiram Miller Showalter, George Harrison Shull, Edmund Ware Sennott, Marion Storm, Charles Fletcher Swingle, James Herbert Taylor, Norman Taylor, Raymond Leech Taylor, Frans Verdoon, Edward Norris Wentworth, and Thomas W. Whitaker.
Additional papers of O. E. White can be found under 6/9/2.831, Administrative files of the directors, vice-directors and acting directors of the Blandy Experimental Farm ... 1926-1974.
Organization
The collection consists of 15 Hollinger boxes. White's arrangement, with slight modifications, has been maintained. The papers are arranged alphabetically within the following series: I. Correspondence re John Burrough, II. Personal and General Correspondence, III. Articles, Reviews, and Manuscripts, and IV. Blandy Experimental Farm Correspondence.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence re John Burroughs
  - Correspondence: John Burroughs 1902-ca. 1919 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: re John Burroughs 1919-1925 (Box 1)
  - John Burroughs, "A Critical Glance Into Darwin" ca. 1920 (Box 1)
- Series II: Personal and General Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Aa-Ary 1923-1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Atchison, Earlene 1942-1947, 1948-1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Ate-Baldwin 1928-1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Ban-Bot 1912-1924 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Bowden, Wray M. 1937-1947 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Bowm-Bri 1936-1955 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Bro-Byrd 1913-1955 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Ca-Com 1910-1955 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Con-Cy 1912-1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: D 1914-1952 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: East, Edward Murray 1914-1937 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Ecc-Fli 1914-1955 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Flory, Walter 1932-1949 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Fra-Gaiser 1914-1955 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Gau-Gra 1919-1955 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Gregory, Margaret 1939-1955 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Gregory, Walton C. 1940-1951 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Ha-Hey 1922-1954 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Hi-Hy 1919-1954 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: I-J 1918-1955 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: K 1923-1955 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: L 1914-1955 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Ma-Mer 1926-1955 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Mey-Mon ca. 1923-1955 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Moo-My 1922-1954 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: N-O 1917-1955 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Ph-Py 1923-1955 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Pa-Per 1936-1955 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Q-Ray 1918-1955 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Re-Ry 1919-1955 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Sa-Se 1922-1955 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Sh-Si 1921-1955 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Sl-Sp 1921-1955 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: St-Sy 1922-1955 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Taa-Taylor, N. 1922-1955 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Taylor, R.-V 1917-1955 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Wa-Whitaker 1922-1955 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: White family ca. 1921-1955 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous letters, papers, etc. ca. 1918-1955 (Box 9)
- Series III: Articles, Reviews, and Manuscripts
  - Book Reviews ca. 1927-ca. 1929 (Box 9)
  - Criticisms on Belling's Translation of an Article by Mendel 1925 (Box 9)
  - "Fasciation: Its Distribution and Causes" May, 1947 (Box 9)
  - Mulford Exploration Journal, pp. 1-465 June, 1921-April, 1922, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Short Articles and Notes ca. 1929-ca. 1951 (Box 10)
  - Economic Plants: "Origin of Cultivated Plants"; "Viruses"; "Fungi"; "Embryophyta"; "Monocots"; and "Dicots" n.d., 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Economic Plants: "Dicots" n.d., 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Economic Plants"Illustrations and Photos" n.d., 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Economic Plants"Illustrations and Photos" n.d., 2 folders (Box 13)
- Series IV: Blandy Experimental Farm Correspondence
  - Correspondence: A-E 1930-1954 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: F-G 1936-1951 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: H-K 1931-1954 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: L 1930-1955 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: M-N 1932-1954 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence: P-R 1932-1952 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence: S 1929-1954 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence: T-Z 1934-1951 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1936-1948 (Box 14)
  - Blandy Experimental Farm: "Future File" 1953 (Box 14)
- Restricted Files n.d., 4 folders (Box 15)